<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.6.2">Jekyll</generator><link href="/gndem.org/fr/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="/gndem.org/fr/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2018-08-04T17:22:03-04:00</updated><id>/gndem.org/</id><title type="html">Global Network of Domestic Election Monitors</title><subtitle>The Global Network of Domestic Election Monitors connects over 245 regional networks and individual nonpartisan citizen observation groups to share best practices and further our common aspirations for representative, responsive, transparent, democratic governance.</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Amid Political Tensions, CRTA’s PVT Confirms Preliminary Results</title><link href="/gndem.org/fr/2018/07/21/amid-political-tensions-crta-s-pvt-confirms-preliminary-results.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Amid Political Tensions, CRTA’s PVT Confirms Preliminary Results" /><published>2018-07-21T18:10:55-04:00</published><updated>2018-07-21T18:10:55-04:00</updated><id>/gndem.org/2018/07/21/amid-political-tensions-crta-s-pvt-confirms-preliminary-results</id><content type="html" xml:base="/gndem.org/2018/07/21/amid-political-tensions-crta-s-pvt-confirms-preliminary-results.html">&lt;p&gt;Serbians turned out to vote on April 2, 2017 to elect their next president. With elections called only a month before the date, the political stakes were high between then Prime Minister Aleksandar Vucic and a number of opposition candidates. The election was seen by many as a referendum on the policies and actions of Vucic, whose Serbian Progressive Party (SNS) represents the largest party in the ruling coalition in parliament after retaining their majority in the 2016 parliamentary elections. With a limited amount of time for candidates to campaign and amid a partisan political environment, Serbian citizen observer group and GNDEM member the &lt;a href=&quot;http://crta.rs/en/home-2/&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Center for Research, Transparency and Accountability&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; (CRTA) mobilized the mission &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.gradjaninastrazi.rs/&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;“Citizens on Watch”&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; quickly to monitor the campaign period and conduct a parallel vote tabulation (PVT) on election day. Following the election, CRTA is monitoring post-election developments.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The election presented a unique situation for CRTA. While many elections are typically monitored by both international and citizen election observers, one of the main international observer organizations in Europe, the Organization for Security and Cooperation in Europe (OSCE) Office for Democratic Institutions and Human Rights (ODIHR), &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.balkaninsight.com/en/article/dozen-foreign-observers-to-monitor-serbian-elections-03-28-2017&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;announced&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; they would only be sending an assessment mission to observe the elections in Serbia. The 2017 election in Serbia saw fewer election monitors than in previous elections, putting additional attention and pressure on CRTA to present a non-partisan, accurate assessment of the election process.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Pre-election environment&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With a shorter &lt;a href=&quot;http://crta.rs/wp-content/uploads/2017/04/CRTA-Citizens-on-Watch-Preliminary-Report-on-Election-Day-Monitoring.pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;pre-election period&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, CRTA’s 60 long-term observers only had a few weeks to monitor election preparations, the conduct of the campaign and the general political environment. The campaign period, while short, was notably marked by an uneven playing field and huge imbalance, creating unequal opportunities for candidates to campaign. CRTA found a significant number of cases where public officials on local level, directly or indirectly, campaigned for Vucic using their official position. CRTA also found that Vucic enjoyed significantly &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nytimes.com/2017/03/30/world/europe/serbia-prepares-to-elect-a-president-amid-a-murky-media-landscape.html&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;less negative coverage&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; on the front page of newspapers than the top two opposition candidates. They also found that given the short time period, the campaign was very intense and grew heated with reports of voter intimidation and hate speech.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Election day observation&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On election day, CRTA deployed 900 observers to a random, representative sample of 450 polling stations across the country to observe the conduct of the election, from the opening of stations through the completion of counting. In addition, CRTA deployed 60 mobile teams in every district to monitor election-related incidents occurring outside of polling stations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before and on election day, CRTA used social media, namely &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.facebook.com/gradjaninastrazi/?hc_ref=PAGES_TIMELINE&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Facebook&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;and &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/NaStrazi&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Twitter&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; for the “Citizens on Watch” program, to disseminate &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.facebook.com/gradjaninastrazi/videos/730886050406318/&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;videos&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and infographics, which helped to easily communicate their findings and data from the pre-election period and throughout election day. CRTA also broadcast their press conferences and infographics throughout the day on Facebook Live, bringing the important events to a different type of medium and engaging with an audience who may not have otherwise followed developments.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;CRTA’s observers &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.gradjaninastrazi.rs/wp-content/uploads/2017/04/CRTA-Citizens-on-Watch-Preliminary-Report-on-Election-Day-Monitoring.pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;found&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; that 87% of polling stations opened on time, with only one polling station experiencing significant delays (more than two hours). While 44% of polling stations were accessible to persons with disabilities, representing a slight increase since the 2016 parliamentary elections.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Observers were shown empty ballot boxes before they were sealed in 100% of polling stations, and found that voting irregularities, such as voting without identification documents or campaign materials within 50 meters of the polling station, occurred in only 3% of polling stations. While these problems were limited, CRTA did find that there were isolated cases of voters experiencing issues with the voters list, such as not finding their names on the list or the electronic list, which CRTA highlighted has remained a problem following the 2016 parliamentary elections.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Following polling station closure and the completion of counting, observers obtained and sent polling station level results, where CRTA’s leaders in Belgrade quickly analyzed the findings. Due in large part to effective training of election day observers, CRTA received a 100% response rate from observers on election night, helping them to rapidly determine the results of the PVT.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The PVT results were consistent with preliminary results from Serbia’s Republic Electoral Commission (RIK), which showed that Vucic won the first round election and cleared the 50%+1 necessary to avoid a runoff election. While their observation of the process on election day showed irregularities, CRTA determined they were not significant enough to alter the election results.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Post-election&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Following election day and the announcement of results, protests erupted in the capital, Belgrade, and other cities around Serbia protesting Vucic’s win. Many of the protesters claimed that the election had been fraudulent, lamenting the election commission and the media for their involvement in creating an unfair election. CRTA’s assessment of election day processes and the PVT, as well as their ability to speak to the nationwide conduct of the election, revealed that the irregularities observed on election day specifically would not have altered the eventual election results.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, CRTA’s observation of the pre-election period exposed significant flaws in the process with a campaign marked by several types of unequal treatment of candidates. These issues should be addressed by electoral and political stakeholders and the media, and should be assessed for how the issues could impact future elections.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the days and weeks following the election, CRTA has continued to monitor the post-election environment. While protests continued, CRTA sought to ease tensions by &lt;a href=&quot;http://crta.rs/crta-files-the-request-for-access-to-polling-board-records/&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;requesting access&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; to polling station records in order to compare them with the results photographed and acquired by CRTA’s observers. CRTA also filed 18 complaints related to election day violations and irregularities, of which three were adopted by the RIK.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the coming weeks, CRTA will release their final report on the presidential election, in which they will also offer recommendations to electoral stakeholders, including the media and election commission, on improvements and changes to be made before the next elections.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="Parallel Vote Tabulation (PVT)" /><category term="Serbia" /><category term="Campaign and Political Environment Monitoring" /><category term="Central &amp; Eastern Europe" /><summary type="html">Serbians turned out to vote on April 2, 2017 to elect their next president. With elections called only a month before the date, the political stakes were high between then Prime Minister Aleksandar Vucic and a number of opposition candidates. The election was seen by many as a referendum on the policies and actions of Vucic, whose Serbian Progressive Party (SNS) represents the largest party in the ruling coalition in parliament after retaining their majority in the 2016 parliamentary elections. With a limited amount of time for candidates to campaign and amid a partisan political environment, Serbian citizen observer group and GNDEM member the Center for Research, Transparency and Accountability (CRTA) mobilized the mission “Citizens on Watch” quickly to monitor the campaign period and conduct a parallel vote tabulation (PVT) on election day. Following the election, CRTA is monitoring post-election developments.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">GNDEM Members Shared Best Practices, Experiences in the Balkans and Eurasia</title><link href="/gndem.org/fr/2018/07/21/gndem-members-shared-best-practices-experiences-in-the-balkans-and-eurasia.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="GNDEM Members Shared Best Practices, Experiences in the Balkans and Eurasia" /><published>2018-07-21T18:09:10-04:00</published><updated>2018-07-21T18:09:10-04:00</updated><id>/gndem.org/2018/07/21/gndem-members-shared-best-practices-experiences-in-the-balkans-and-eurasia</id><content type="html" xml:base="/gndem.org/2018/07/21/gndem-members-shared-best-practices-experiences-in-the-balkans-and-eurasia.html">&lt;p&gt;From April 15-17, GNDEM members and citizen election observer groups from Central and Eastern Europe and Eurasia gathered in Belgrade, Serbia for the CEE Elections Academy. 12 citizen observer groups from 10 countries attended the three-day academy, including 10 GNDEM members: &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.gndem.org/sdc&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Society for Democratic Culture&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; (Albania), &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.kzln.org.al/&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Coalition for Free and Fair Elections and for Sustainable Democracy&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; (Albania); &lt;a href=&quot;http://podlupom.org/v2/&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Center for Civic Initiatives (CCI) / Coalition for Free and Fair Election - Pod Lupom&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; (Bosnia and Herzegovina); the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.isfed.ge/&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;International Society for Fair Elections and Democracy&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; (Georgia); &lt;a href=&quot;http://gong.hr/en/&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;GONG&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; (Croatia); &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.most.org.mk/index.php?lang=en&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Citizens Association MOST&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;(Macedonia); &lt;a href=&quot;http://cemi.org.me/en/o-nama/&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;CeMI Center for Monitoring and Research&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; (Montenegro); &lt;a href=&quot;http://crta.rs/sr/pocetna/&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Center for Research, Transparency and Accountability&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; (Serbia), &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.enemo.eu/en/members/members/30-serbia-center-for-free-elections-and-democracy&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Center for Free Elections and Democracy&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; (Serbia); and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.oporaua.org/en/&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Civil Network OPORA&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; (Ukraine).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Recent elections in the Western Balkans have demonstrated that the electoral process in the region is vulnerable to administrative abuse in such areas as voter registration, media neutrality, use of state resources, and manipulation of electoral bodies. These deficits jeopardize democratic progress. As misconduct has continued to expand beyond election day and further into the pre-election period, citizen observers have been adapting to the changing environment to better monitor irregularities during key pre-election processes, including voter registration, campaign finance and the media. Their efforts have begun to re-build waning public confidence in electoral processes. During the first day, focus on long-term observation and the role of long-term observers (LTOs), representatives from OPORA, ISFED, CRTA and Pod Lupom shared best practices on organizing LTO forms, compiling manuals of all necessary information for LTOs, and developing a centralized database that can easily process and analyze LTO reports that are sent in. A representative from ISFED also highlighted the testing that the group does to ensure that LTOs understand their assignment, the reporting schedule and method, and were properly trained. All citizen observer groups shared ideas and insights related to their own long-term observation efforts, while also recognizing challenges and areas for growth ahead of future elections. At the end of the day, groups discussed the issue of fake news and disinformation and how it presents itself throughout the electoral process. Participants shared their thoughts on its impact on elections, and citizen observers’ role in monitoring and mitigating its effects.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The second day of the academy focus on election day observation and specifically the advancing practice of systematic election observation through sample-based observation (SBO) or parallel vote tabulation (PVT). Presenters emphasized key principles of election day observation, including that observers must be stationary and remain at the polling station through opening, voting and counting processes; using a random, representative sample of polling stations; and speaking only from information gained from observers. Representatives from ISFED, OPORA and CRTA also shared the importance testing election day infrastructure and observers’ preparedness for election day, such as observers’ familiarity with reporting procedures and the functionality of databases, through simulations, written tests and verbal tests prior to election day. These types of testing ensure that all systems operate properly and mitigate the potential for major issues on election day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The final day led to discussions on post-election activities, as well as external communications and open election data. CRTA shared their pre-election and election day strategies for sharing information on social media, including when, how and what type of content was shared online (you can check out content from their observation of the 2017 elections &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.facebook.com/gradjaninastrazi/?hc_ref=PAGES_TIMELINE&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;here&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;). Groups also shared their thoughts on newer methods of engaging citizens through livestreaming and the use of infographics to easily grab the attention of social media users. Building off of the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.openelectiondata.net/en/&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Open Election Data Initiative&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, participants from Albania, Macedonia, Georgia, Serbia and Ukraine shared ways in which their groups have used election data that was made available to further support their election observation activities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Following the academy, participants expressed a willingness to learn more about voter registration, campaign finance monitoring and the statistical principles of systematic election observation. Groups identified open election data and external communications as areas that could further amplify their observation efforts during the electoral cycle. This peer-to-peer learning opportunity amongst GNDEM members proved to be very useful, where members can take the innovative ideas, information and tools discussed at the academy and apply them for current and future election observation activities within their countries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The National Democratic Institute (NDI) hosted the academy, with funding from USAID.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="CeSID" /><category term="GONG" /><category term="ISFED" /><category term="MOST" /><category term="OPORA" /><category term="Pod Lupom" /><category term="Central &amp; Eastern Europe" /><category term="Eurasia" /><summary type="html">From April 15-17, GNDEM members and citizen election observer groups from Central and Eastern Europe and Eurasia gathered in Belgrade, Serbia for the CEE Elections Academy. 12 citizen observer groups from 10 countries attended the three-day academy, including 10 GNDEM members: Society for Democratic Culture (Albania), Coalition for Free and Fair Elections and for Sustainable Democracy (Albania); Center for Civic Initiatives (CCI) / Coalition for Free and Fair Election - Pod Lupom (Bosnia and Herzegovina); the International Society for Fair Elections and Democracy (Georgia); GONG (Croatia); Citizens Association MOST(Macedonia); CeMI Center for Monitoring and Research (Montenegro); Center for Research, Transparency and Accountability (Serbia), Center for Free Elections and Democracy (Serbia); and Civil Network OPORA (Ukraine).</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">GNDEM Calls on Government of Cambodia to Stop Pressuring Citizen Election Observers</title><link href="/gndem.org/fr/2018/07/21/gndem-calls-on-government-of-cambodia-to-stop-pressuring-citizen-election-observers.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="GNDEM Calls on Government of Cambodia to Stop Pressuring Citizen Election Observers" /><published>2018-07-21T18:07:23-04:00</published><updated>2018-07-21T18:07:23-04:00</updated><id>/gndem.org/2018/07/21/gndem-calls-on-government-of-cambodia-to-stop-pressuring-citizen-election-observers</id><content type="html" xml:base="/gndem.org/2018/07/21/gndem-calls-on-government-of-cambodia-to-stop-pressuring-citizen-election-observers.html">&lt;p&gt;The Global Network of Domestic Election Monitors (GNDEM) has learned from credible news reports that Cambodia’s Interior Ministry has been called upon to take measures against The Situation Room (a platform of over 40 nongovernmental organizations) for its election monitoring activities focused on the recent Commune Council elections. Included among those organizations is a GNDEM member, the Committee for Free and Fair Elections in Cambodia (COMFREL).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Situation Room issued on 24 June 2017 its &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.comfrel.org/eng/index.php?option=com_content&amp;amp;view=article&amp;amp;id=821:statement-overall-and-ultimate-assessment-on-commune-council-election-for-the-4th-mandate-restrictions-on-political-freedom-and-limits-to-fairness-but-improved-election-management-&amp;amp;catid=188:other&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;assessment&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; of the Commune Council elections. That report noted the elections had significantly improved, including that polling, counting, results reporting and other processes were made more transparent than previous elections. It also offered a number of criticisms of the electoral environment, focused on pre-election factors, and concluded that elections in Cambodia cannot yet be considered free and fair, and it offered recommendations for improving elections. On 28 June, the Situation Room issued a press release reaffirming its political impartiality.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cambodia has long recognized citizen election monitoring organizations and accredited them to observe elections. Citizens not only have a right to genuine elections, they have a right to know whether their elections are credible, and that can only be accomplished through citizen observers, the media, and political party representatives scrutinizing the various processes and factors that make up the electoral process, including the electoral environment. That requires, among other things, exercising the right of association and the freedom of expression in seeking, receiving and imparting information. GNDEM’s &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.gndem.org/sites/default/files/declaration/Declaration_of_Global_Principles_0.pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Declaration of Global Principles&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; for Nonpartisan Election Observation and Monitoring by Citizen Organizations, which is endorsed by COMFREL and 293 other organizations and networks from 93 countries and which key international organizations support, including the UN Secretariat and others, requires political impartiality and accuracy, as does the Declaration’s Code of Conduct.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;GNDEM reiterates that nonpartisan citizen election observation requires respect for the freedoms of association and expression in order to conduct its vital roles in: promoting credible, peaceful elections; advancing electoral integrity; and enhancing public confidence and participation in elections. GNDEM therefore calls on the Government of Cambodia to stop pressuring citizen election monitoring organizations and their leaders. We also urge others in the international community to call on the Government of Cambodia to not pressure citizen election monitors.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="Asia" /><category term="COMFREL" /><category term="Cambodia" /><summary type="html">The Global Network of Domestic Election Monitors (GNDEM) has learned from credible news reports that Cambodia’s Interior Ministry has been called upon to take measures against The Situation Room (a platform of over 40 nongovernmental organizations) for its election monitoring activities focused on the recent Commune Council elections. Included among those organizations is a GNDEM member, the Committee for Free and Fair Elections in Cambodia (COMFREL).</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">GNDEM Coordinating Committee Convenes for Fifth DoGP Implementation Meeting</title><link href="/gndem.org/fr/2018/07/21/gndem-coordinating-committee-convenes-for-fifth-dogp-implementation-meeting.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="GNDEM Coordinating Committee Convenes for Fifth DoGP Implementation Meeting" /><published>2018-07-21T18:04:44-04:00</published><updated>2018-07-21T18:04:44-04:00</updated><id>/gndem.org/2018/07/21/gndem-coordinating-committee-convenes-for-fifth-dogp-implementation-meeting</id><content type="html" xml:base="/gndem.org/2018/07/21/gndem-coordinating-committee-convenes-for-fifth-dogp-implementation-meeting.html">&lt;p&gt;GNDEM convened its Fifth Implementation Meeting of the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.gndem.org/declaration-of-global-principles&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Declaration of Global Principles for Nonpartisan Citizen Election Observation&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; (DoGP) from June 27-28, 2017 in Tbilisi, Georgia. Participants in the annual meeting included GNDEM Coordinating Committee members from la Red de Observación e Integridad Electoral - Acuerdo de Lima (RedOIE) (formerly &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.gndem.org/es/acuerdo-de-lima&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Acuerdo de Lima&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;) in Latin America and the Caribbean, the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.arabnde.org/arabic/&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Arab Network for Democratic Elections&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; (ANDE), &lt;a href=&quot;http://anfrel.org/&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Asian Network for Free Elections&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; (ANFREL), &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.facebook.com/EastandHornofAfricaElectionObservationNetwork/&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;East and Horn of Africa Election Observers Network&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; (E-HORN), &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.arabew.org/english/&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Election Network in the Arab Region&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; (ENAR), &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.enemo.eu/en/home&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;European Network of Election Monitoring Organizations&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; (ENEMO), &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.epde.org/en/&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;European Platform for Democratic Elections&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; (EPDE), &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.facebook.com/SADC.ESN/&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Electoral Support Network of Southern Africa&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; (ESN-SA) and &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.waeon.org/&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;West Africa Election Observers Network&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; (WAEON). Following the two-day meeting, GNDEM participants also took part in a Global Electoral Integrity Dialogue, a two-day exchange convening citizen observers, international observers and election management bodies on open election data - co-hosted by the &lt;a href=&quot;http://cesko.ge/eng&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Central Election Commission of Georgia&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; (CEC).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Following a meeting among the GNDEM Board (established at last year’s &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.gndem.org/node/7238/&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;meeting&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; in Bali), the Implementation Meeting allowed the Coordinating Committee to focus on the structure of the network itself, how the network can ensure all members adhere to the DoGP, and to determine how GNDEM’s working groups can make progress on action plans between meetings. In addition to discussions regarding GNDEM’s internal organization, the Coordinating Committee was able to discuss advancements and experiences related to advocacy for open election data, activities members have undertaken during periods between elections, and efforts related to solidarity and support for members operating in closed or closing spaces.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During an open discussion on solidarity and credibility, a representative from &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.epde.org/en/&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;EPDE&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; outlined the challenges associated with fake election observer groups and government-organized NGOs (GONGOs). She emphasized that GNDEM has a role in promoting credible election observation, and ensuring that members are adhering to the principles they endorsed. Joe Keyrouz of ANDE and the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.lade.org.lb/LADE.aspx?lang=en-us&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Lebanese Association for Democratic Elections&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; (LADE) focused on the need for GNDEM to better solidify a membership structure, and proposed an accreditation system for members. While the Coordinating Committee agreed that it is important to ensure that only credible groups are permitted to become GNDEM members, they also proposed an accreditation system that is straightforward, both for the leadership to implement and for current and prospective members to apply. The working group on membership and structure is anticipated to further flesh out criteria and proposals over the next year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&quot;http://cemi.org.me/en/&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Center for Monitoring and Research&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; (CeMI) in Montenegro, &lt;a href=&quot;http://moe.org.co/&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Misión de Observación Electoral&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; (MOE) in Colombia and &lt;a href=&quot;http://anfrel.org/&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;ANFREL&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; provided insight and experience-sharing on using official and open election data to further election observation efforts and initiatives. In Montenegro and the Balkans in general, more work needs to be done around open election data, yet CeMI shared that they also publish their own data from observers in an effort to be transparent with the public. ANFREL is currently building off of last year’s &lt;a href=&quot;http://aesforum.anfrel.org/&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Asian Electoral Stakeholders Forum&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;(AESF), where the Bali Commitments presented eight keys to electoral integrity related to transparency and open election data. ANFREL hopes to further engage EMBs and to facilitate dialogue on best practices related to sharing open election data. MOE in Colombia developed an online application called “Cuentas Claras”, which provides citizens with access to campaign finance data, allowing them to see how campaign funds are being spent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During the third panel, representatives from the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.isfed.ge/&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;International Society for Fair Elections and Democracy&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; (ISFED) in Georgia, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.facebook.com/accion.ciudadana.gt/&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Acción Ciudadana&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; in Guatemala and &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.mesnmw.org/&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Malawi Electoral Support Network&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; (MESN) shared how their organizations have stayed engaged between elections and have cultivated their elections networks to monitor other political processes or advance electoral reforms. ISFED shared how they used data-driven practices and forged relationships with parties and other CSOs to advocate for electoral reforms in Georgia, both after the 2012 elections and during this year’s constitutional reform process. In Guatemala, AC found that campaign finance presented a big challenge in the country around recent elections, and shared their strategies for electoral reform advocacy around campaign finance and the justice system. In Malawi, MESN was part of a task force on electoral reform following problems observed during the 2014 elections. MESN not only looked at issues that would need to be legally addressed, but also at improving administrative matters before the next elections to improve the electoral process.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the conclusion of the meeting, the Coordinating Committee developed their proposed structure for continuing activities over the next year, electing Joe Keyrouz of ANDE and &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.lade.org.lb/LADE.aspx?lang=en-us&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;LADE&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; as the new Chair, and Carol Werunga of E-HORN and the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.khrc.or.ke/&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Kenya Human Rights Commission&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; (KHRC) as Vice Chair. The Coordinating Committee also restructured the working groups based on discussions at the meeting. The Solidarity Working Group, chaired by Koul Panha of ANFREL and the Committee for Free and Fair Elections in Cambodia (COMFREL), will continue to support members in closing spaces, and to respond to threats to citizen election observation as a practice. The newly created “Membership and Structure” Working Group, chaired by Zlatko Vujović of ENEMO and the Center for Monitoring and Research (CeMI) in Montenegro, will focus on the development, revision and finalization of a set of by-laws for the network, as well as develop a set of criteria for GNDEM membership. The Advocacy Working Group, chaired by Amer Bani Amer of ENAR and Al-Hayat in Jordan, will continue to focus on issues related to open election data, yet could expand to include other advocacy efforts important to citizen observers. In years past, a Methodology Working Group has focused on a topic voted on by the Coordinating Committee. While this year’s panel focused on inter-election accountability initiatives, the scope of the working group has broadened to “best practices,” which will focus on disseminating strong examples and case studies in advanced election observation practices throughout all GNDEM members.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For more information on these working groups and GNDEM activities, stay tuned for the monthly GNDEM newsletter or email &lt;a href=&quot;http://gndem.ndi.org/gndem@ndi.org&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;gndem@ndi.org&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="Acuerdo de Lima" /><category term="ANDE" /><category term="ANFREL" /><category term="E-HORN" /><category term="ENAR" /><category term="ENEMO" /><category term="EPDE" /><category term="SADC ESN" /><category term="WAEON" /><category term="Global" /><summary type="html">GNDEM convened its Fifth Implementation Meeting of the Declaration of Global Principles for Nonpartisan Citizen Election Observation (DoGP) from June 27-28, 2017 in Tbilisi, Georgia. Participants in the annual meeting included GNDEM Coordinating Committee members from la Red de Observación e Integridad Electoral - Acuerdo de Lima (RedOIE) (formerly Acuerdo de Lima) in Latin America and the Caribbean, the Arab Network for Democratic Elections (ANDE), Asian Network for Free Elections (ANFREL), East and Horn of Africa Election Observers Network (E-HORN), Election Network in the Arab Region (ENAR), European Network of Election Monitoring Organizations (ENEMO), European Platform for Democratic Elections (EPDE), Electoral Support Network of Southern Africa (ESN-SA) and West Africa Election Observers Network (WAEON). Following the two-day meeting, GNDEM participants also took part in a Global Electoral Integrity Dialogue, a two-day exchange convening citizen observers, international observers and election management bodies on open election data - co-hosted by the Central Election Commission of Georgia (CEC).</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">GNDEM Hosts Two Global Events in Tbilisi, Georgia</title><link href="/gndem.org/fr/2018/07/21/gndem-hosts-two-global-events-in-tbilisi-georgia.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="GNDEM Hosts Two Global Events in Tbilisi, Georgia" /><published>2018-07-21T18:03:24-04:00</published><updated>2018-07-21T18:03:24-04:00</updated><id>/gndem.org/2018/07/21/gndem-hosts-two-global-events-in-tbilisi-georgia</id><content type="html" xml:base="/gndem.org/2018/07/21/gndem-hosts-two-global-events-in-tbilisi-georgia.html">&lt;p&gt;From June 27-28, 2017, the GNDEM Coordinating Committee, representing all nine regional networks, convened in Tbilisi, Georgia for the Fifth Implementation Meeting of the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.gndem.org/declaration-of-global-principles&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Declaration of Global Principles for Nonpartisan Citizen Election Observation&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; (DoGP). Building off of previous Implementation Meetings held in Bali, Johannesburg, Mexico City and Beirut, the Coordinating Committee was able to discuss recent challenges, share experiences and best practices from their election observation work and develop action items for the coming year. Topics of discussion this year included solidarity and credibility among citizen observers; membership criteria for members to ensure activity and credibility; advocacy for electoral transparency, specifically focused on open election data; and inter-election accountability initiatives.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The GNDEM Coordinating Committee also elected a new Chair, Joe Keyrouz of ANDE and the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.lade.org.lb/LADE.aspx?lang=en-us&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Lebanese Association for Democratic Elections&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; (LADE), and a new Vice Chair, Carol Werunga of E-HORN and the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.khrc.or.ke/&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Kenya Human Rights Commission&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; (KHRC). Their election comes after a year of leadership from Alejandra Barrios Cabrera of la Red de Observación e Integridad Electoral - Acuerdo de Lima (RedOIE) (formerly Acuerdo de Lima) and Misión de Observación Electoral (MOE) in Colombia as Chair, and from Steve Duwa-Phiri of ESN-SA and the Malawi Electoral Support Network (MESN) as Vice Chair. Participants in the annual meeting included GNDEM Coordinating Committee members from la Red de Observación e Integridad Electoral - Acuerdo de Lima (RedOIE) (formerly &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.gndem.org/es/acuerdo-de-lima&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Acuerdo de Lima&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;) in Latin America and the Caribbean, the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.arabnde.org/arabic/&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Arab Network for Democratic Elections&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; (ANDE), &lt;a href=&quot;http://anfrel.org/&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Asian Network for Free Elections&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; (ANFREL), &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.facebook.com/EastandHornofAfricaElectionObservationNetwork/&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;East and Horn of Africa Election Observers Network&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; (E-HORN), &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.arabew.org/english/&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Election Network in the Arab Region&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; (ENAR), &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.enemo.eu/en/home&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;European Network of Election Monitoring Organizations&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; (ENEMO), &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.epde.org/en/&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;European Platform for Democratic Elections&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; (EPDE), &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.facebook.com/SADC.ESN/&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Electoral Support Network of Southern Africa&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; (ESN-SA) and &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.waeon.org/&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;West Africa Election Observers Network&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; (WAEON).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.gndem.org/GNDEM_Meeting_2017&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Read more about the DoGP Implementation Meeting and access meeting materials.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Following the Implementation Meeting, GNDEM co-hosted the Global Electoral Integrity Dialogue (GEID) along with the &lt;a href=&quot;http://cesko.ge/eng&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Central Election Commission of Georgia&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; (CEC). The Dialogue convened citizen observers, international observers and election management bodies (EMBs) from 25 countries in Tbilisi, Georgia to discuss electoral transparency through open election data. Plenary sessions focused on Transparency through Open Election Data, Open Election Data throughout the Electoral Cycle, and Challenges of Disinformation to Electoral Integrity. These panels provided each of the three electoral communities to share best practices, case studies and challenges from their experience, while also looking forward to how new ideas or practices could be implemented in the future. Subsequent breakout groups also allowed for more targeted discussion among colleagues on challenges and benefits to open election data, specific concerns and opportunities on using and opening different types of election data throughout the electoral cycle, and solutions and multi-stakeholder engagement on combating disinformation. GNDEM members from Ukraine, Georgia, Guatemala, Jordan, Colombia, Moldova, Lebanon and Kenya were able to serve on panels and lead discussions, showcasing not only their organizations’ experience on advocating for and utilizing open election data, but the growing acknowledgment and practice of providing and using open election data. The Dialogue concluded with regional-level breakouts, where participants discussed specific regional challenges on these topics and possible solutions they as electoral practitioners could undertake to mitigate and solve these issues.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">From June 27-28, 2017, the GNDEM Coordinating Committee, representing all nine regional networks, convened in Tbilisi, Georgia for the Fifth Implementation Meeting of the Declaration of Global Principles for Nonpartisan Citizen Election Observation (DoGP). Building off of previous Implementation Meetings held in Bali, Johannesburg, Mexico City and Beirut, the Coordinating Committee was able to discuss recent challenges, share experiences and best practices from their election observation work and develop action items for the coming year. Topics of discussion this year included solidarity and credibility among citizen observers; membership criteria for members to ensure activity and credibility; advocacy for electoral transparency, specifically focused on open election data; and inter-election accountability initiatives.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Coalition Observes Kyrgyzstan’s First Peaceful Transition of Power</title><link href="/gndem.org/fr/2018/07/21/the-coalition-observes-kyrgyzstan-s-first-peaceful-transition-of-power.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Coalition Observes Kyrgyzstan’s First Peaceful Transition of Power" /><published>2018-07-21T18:00:54-04:00</published><updated>2018-07-21T18:00:54-04:00</updated><id>/gndem.org/2018/07/21/the-coalition-observes-kyrgyzstan-s-first-peaceful-transition-of-power</id><content type="html" xml:base="/gndem.org/2018/07/21/the-coalition-observes-kyrgyzstan-s-first-peaceful-transition-of-power.html">&lt;p&gt;On October 15, voters in Kyrgyzstan turned out to vote in what would ultimately be the first peaceful transfer of power between elected presidents in the country - and Central Asia - since the fall of the Soviet Union. Following protests in 2005 and 2010 that led to the ouster of the presidents at the time, a new constitution was passed in 2010 introducing a strong parliament to better place checks on the presidency.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the 2017 presidential election, incumbent president, Almazbek Atambaev, was barred from running again due to constitutional term limits. His prime minister, Sooronbay Jeenbekov, stepped down to run as the Social Democratic Party of Kyrgyzstan (SDPK)’s presidential candidate. Initially, 59 candidates filed to run for president; however, the Central Election Commission eventually invalidated a number of candidates due to not obtaining enough signatures or failing the Kyrgyz language test needed to officially stand on the ballot. One of the main opposition candidates from the Ata-Meken (Fatherland) party, Omurbek Tekebaev, was ultimately sentenced to eight years in prison on &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.rferl.org/a/kyrgyzstan-tekebaev-8-year-sentence-/28680250.html&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;corruption charges&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, which the party alleges were filed to keep him from running for president. Ultimately, 13 candidates appeared on the November ballot; most ran as independent candidates.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Long-term observers monitor the pre-election environment&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For this pivotal and important election, local citizen observer group the &lt;a href=&quot;http://coalition.kg/&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Coalition for Democracy and Civil Society&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; (or the Coalition) deployed 60 &lt;a href=&quot;http://coalition.kg/en/2017/10/03/%D0%BD%D0%BE%D0%B2%D0%BE%D1%81%D1%82%D0%B82/&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;long-term observers&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; across all 57 districts of the country to assess the electoral environment, including preparations and functions by the Central Election Commission (CEC) and territorial election commissions (TECs), as well as the campaign period. LTOs found that most CEC processes were transparent and open to observation, yet others, such as verifying signatures for candidates, were not. They assessed gender and party composition of TECs over the pre-electoral period, as well as quorum for commission meetings. During the campaign period, the Coalition’s LTOs looked at the number of party/candidate headquarters and billboards, and collected data on incidents of pressure, threats or vote-buying. LTOs also monitored the use of state resources for campaign purposes, recording details of situations and instances where this occurred.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During the pre-election period, the Coalition also used sampling methodology to assess changes to the voters list. The Coalition drew a sample of 350 polling stations that LTOs visited twice (for the first time when the voters list was posted for the public to check, and the second time a few days before election day when the voters list was closed). Using reports submitted by LTOs, the Coalition was able to determine that there was a .64% increase in the number of people on the voters list, but were also able to note that there were polling stations where voters lists were not posted on time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Coalition conducts PVT on election day&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On election day, the Coalition deployed 1,000 observers to a random, representative sample of 500 polling stations across the country to conduct a parallel vote tabulation (PVT). Observers reported at assigned times throughout election day and night via structured SMS messages to a central database. This was the Coalition’s first use of SMS reporting for election observation, and they successfully achieved a 100% response rate from all 500 sampled polling stations, a result of multi-level training, preparation and testing of STOs. The Coalition released reports and infographics on their findings from the opening, voting and counting processes, assessing the timely opening of polling stations, polling station staff’s adherence to procedures, voter turnout throughout the day, and any obstacles observers themselves may have faced. Following counting processes, observers texted in the presidential results from their assigned polling stations. The Coalition found that the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.facebook.com/coalitionkg/photos/a.558066237540283.145307.396143763732532/1900893093257584/?type=3&amp;amp;theater&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;PVT results&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; were consistent with the official CEC results within a small margin of error, with SDPK candidate Jeenbekov winning outright in the first round with more than 50% of the vote.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In their preliminary report released on the day after election day, the Coalition elaborated on their election day findings, emphasizing that while the process was largely followed according to procedure, there were some violations and problems with the quality of the voters list. They also highlighted a number of problems during the pre-election period, including that the incumbent president’s campaign for the SDPK candidate “seriously restricted the freedom of competition between candidates.” They also found instances of state employees campaigning for candidates and biased campaign coverage of the national television station, representing a misuse of administrative resources. The Coalition also noted that, for the first time in their history of observation activities, new rules made it harder for their observers to receive accreditation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Enhancing the credibility of observation through livestreaming&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition to sharing infographics and findings on &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.facebook.com/coalitionkg&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Facebook&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, the Coalition livestreamed their call center on election day on &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=2kSI0tVMnLw&amp;amp;feature=youtu.be&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Youtube&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, which showed the work of call center volunteers, as well as findings from observers on the voting process throughout the day. This innovative practice demonstrated the level of sophistication, rigor, and credibility of the Coalition’s work to the general public, and provided a different medium through which they could their findings.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="Coalition for &quot;Democracy and Civil Society&quot;" /><category term="Parallel Vote Tabulation (PVT)" /><category term="Kyrgyzstan" /><category term="Eurasia" /><category term="Monitoring Use of Government Resources and Electoral Advantage" /><summary type="html">On October 15, voters in Kyrgyzstan turned out to vote in what would ultimately be the first peaceful transfer of power between elected presidents in the country - and Central Asia - since the fall of the Soviet Union. Following protests in 2005 and 2010 that led to the ouster of the presidents at the time, a new constitution was passed in 2010 introducing a strong parliament to better place checks on the presidency.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">ANFREL Hosts Roundtable on Transparency and Integrity in Elections</title><link href="/gndem.org/fr/2018/07/21/anfrel-hosts-roundtable-on-transparency-and-integrity-in-elections.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="ANFREL Hosts Roundtable on Transparency and Integrity in Elections" /><published>2018-07-21T17:58:55-04:00</published><updated>2018-07-21T17:58:55-04:00</updated><id>/gndem.org/2018/07/21/anfrel-hosts-roundtable-on-transparency-and-integrity-in-elections</id><content type="html" xml:base="/gndem.org/2018/07/21/anfrel-hosts-roundtable-on-transparency-and-integrity-in-elections.html">&lt;p&gt;From November 10-11, the &lt;a href=&quot;https://anfrel.org/&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Asian Network for Free Elections&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; (ANFREL), in partnership with the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.namfrel.com.ph/v2/home/index1.htm&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;National Citizens’ Movement for Free Elections&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; (NAMFREL), hosted a Roundtable Discussion on Transparency and Integrity in Elections in Manila, Philippines. The roundtable convened election management bodies (EMBs) and citizen election observer groups from five countries - Burma, Cambodia, Indonesia, Philippines and Timor Leste - to discuss opportunities and challenges of advancing open election data in Southeast Asia. . The roundtable builds off of the 2016 Asian Electoral Stakeholder Forum III (AESF III), where the &lt;a href=&quot;https://aesforum.anfrel.org/wp-content/uploads/2017/02/Bali-Commitment.pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Bali commitments&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; - eight open election data-related commitments to bolster electoral integrity and transparency - were drafted.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The roundtable convened GNDEM members &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ticambodia.org/&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Transparency International Cambodia&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; (TIC), &lt;a href=&quot;https://comfrel.org/&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Committee for Free and Fair Elections in Cambodia&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; (COMFREL), the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.pacemyanmar.org/&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;People’s Alliance for Credible Elections&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; (PACE) from Burma and &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.namfrel.com.ph/v2/home/index1.htm&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;NAMFREL&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, as well as &lt;a href=&quot;http://perludem.org/&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Perludem&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.jppr.or.id/profil/&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;People’s Voter Education Networks&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; (JPPR) from Indonesia. Election management body representatives from Timor Leste, Indonesia and the Philippines also attended, allowing for the Indonesian and Filipino groups to directly collaborate with EMBs from their countries on plans for increasing open election data.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The roundtable enabled the electoral stakeholders to review the nine open election data principles as stipulated by the &lt;a href=&quot;http://openelectiondata.net/&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Open Election Data Initiative&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; (OEDI). The EMBs and the observer groups then presented on their respective efforts to promote electoral transparency. The National Election Commission (Comissão Nacional de Eleições, CNE) in Timor Leste shared its efforts to provide results tabulation data in real-time, while making information available online. The General Elections Commission (Komisi Pemilihan Umum, KPU) in Indonesia highlighted its efforts to enhance transparency of their commissioner selection process. They also emphasized their work in creating specific information systems for various parts of the electoral process, such as systems on candidate information and campaign finance. The observer groups also described their challenges to enhancing transparency in elections, yet discussed how they have been able to use available data. The groups from Cambodia expressed concerns and challenges regarding the limited amount of data shared online or made public in any format. In Indonesia, JPPR analyzed campaign finance reports with data made readily available. Perludem manually entered election data to convert it into machine-readable format, and has worked closely with the KPU on open data issues. In Burma, PACE stressed that, while there have been advances in obtaining election data, there remain challenges in opening key election data, such as the voters list.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The civil society and EMB participants then prioritized the electoral integrity challenges and priorities in their countries, and completed an assessment of the openness of related election data with respect to the nine open election data principles. They then brainstormed several recommendations for the future, including promoting greater coordination between regional EMBs, seeking opportunities to share comparative experience between regional peers on implementing open election data policies and practices, and engaging other electoral stakeholders, including additional government officials and political parties. They also advocated for additional open election data materials for groups and EMBs to learn more about best practices across Asia and advanced election data themes, and for leveraging GNDEM to facilitate sharing of open election data resources among election observation groups.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The roundtable participants and ANFREL hope to build off of this event at next year’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.facebook.com/ANFREL/photos/a.228762987137967.76046.179461348734798/1858586770822239/?type=3&amp;amp;theater&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Asian Electoral Stakeholder Forum IV&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, which will convene citizen election observers, election management bodies and other stakeholders in Colombo, Sri Lanka, with the theme “Promoting and Defending Democratic Elections Together.”&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="ANFREL" /><category term="Asia" /><category term="COMFREL" /><category term="NAMFREL" /><category term="PACE" /><summary type="html">From November 10-11, the Asian Network for Free Elections (ANFREL), in partnership with the National Citizens’ Movement for Free Elections (NAMFREL), hosted a Roundtable Discussion on Transparency and Integrity in Elections in Manila, Philippines. The roundtable convened election management bodies (EMBs) and citizen election observer groups from five countries - Burma, Cambodia, Indonesia, Philippines and Timor Leste - to discuss opportunities and challenges of advancing open election data in Southeast Asia. . The roundtable builds off of the 2016 Asian Electoral Stakeholder Forum III (AESF III), where the Bali commitments - eight open election data-related commitments to bolster electoral integrity and transparency - were drafted.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">EU’s Electoral Reform Guide Highlights GNDEM Members’ Strategies</title><link href="/gndem.org/fr/2018/07/21/eu-s-electoral-reform-guide-highlights-gndem-members-strategies.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="EU’s Electoral Reform Guide Highlights GNDEM Members’ Strategies" /><published>2018-07-21T17:56:03-04:00</published><updated>2018-07-21T17:56:03-04:00</updated><id>/gndem.org/2018/07/21/eu-s-electoral-reform-guide-highlights-gndem-members-strategies</id><content type="html" xml:base="/gndem.org/2018/07/21/eu-s-electoral-reform-guide-highlights-gndem-members-strategies.html">&lt;p&gt;Citizen election observation has grown over the past 30 years into a well-established, global movement for enhancing the integrity of elections. Citizen observer groups not only monitor election day processes, but are also involved in pre- and post-election processes and between elections. Groups’ assessments of electoral processes typically include reports at various stages of the election cycle, as well as recommendations on how to best address issues to bring the elections in line with regional and international standards and to improve future electoral processes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, citizen observer groups often turn to other priorities following elections, and – without sustained, targeted demand for reforms – these election observation recommendations can go unaddressed by electoral stakeholders. Citizen observer groups should advocate for reforms throughout the election period, including the post-election period and between elections. They should also monitor the degree to which electoral stakeholders have considered and implemented their recommendations prior to the next election.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Due to the importance of citizen observer groups maintaining a consistent, influential role in advocating for electoral reforms, the European Union’s (EU) ‘Supporting Democracy - A Citizens’ Organisations Programme’ created a &lt;a href=&quot;http://media4democracy.eu/wp-content/uploads/2018/03/Guide-for-Citizen-Observers-on-Electoral-reform.pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Guide for Citizen Observers on Electoral Reform&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, to help them leverage this role.The guide focuses on two types of observation follow-up activities: electoral reform promotion and advocacy, and recommendations tracking and reporting. The former focuses on ways in which groups can strategically develop recommendations, how they can raise awareness of those recommendations, and how they can best target the necessary stakeholders to push for reforms to be implemented. The latter focuses on guidance to groups in monitoring progress of recommendations towards implementation. Ideally, these activities would be undertaken at the same time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The guide provides explanations on a number of different methods citizen observer groups can utilize to promote electoral reform, such as post-election stakeholder roundtables, awareness-raising activities like public events and social media campaigns, election reform committees, expert analyses of legal commentaries, and the issuing of regular public reports on the status of recommendation implementation. It also offers advice on how groups should properly formulate recommendations, emphasizing that when drafting recommendations, it is essential to suggest meaningful reforms to address the problems identified by election observers during the election process. It goes on to describe how to analyze and prioritize recommendations, how to initiate effective post-election dialogue, how to promote electoral reform based on your selected recommendations, and how to maintain a relationship with stakeholders through the establishment of a target audience. The guide also provides helpful resources such as report templates and examples of good recommendations that groups can use as a basis for implementing the best practices in the guide.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The EU’s guide features several GNDEM members, including the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.facebook.com/Malawi.Electoral.Support.Network/&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Malawi Election Support Network&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; (MESN), &lt;a href=&quot;http://accionciudadana.org.gt/&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Acción Ciudadana&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; (AC), the &lt;a href=&quot;http://isfed.ge/&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;International Society for Fair Elections and Democracy&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;(ISFED), &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.bersih.org/&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Bersih 2.0&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.transparencia.org.pe/&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Transparencia Peru&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; (AC), and the &lt;a href=&quot;http://coalition.kg/en/&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Coalition for Democracy and Civil Society&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and their experiences with electoral reform efforts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Following the May 2014 tripartite elections, MESN utilized some of the strategies outlined in this guide. MESN issued a final election report with specific recommendations to address challenges identified through their observation of electoral processes. They then conducted a post-election review process, including three regional dialogue meetings and a national conference to finalize the reform priorities. MESN and the Malawi Election Commission (MEC) then partnered to create a task force to further engage in electoral reform priorities, and finally, in March 2017, the Law Commission submitted its report with draft bills on the laws to be changed, incorporating most of the Task Force’s recommendations. Throughout the process, MESN issued periodic public reports on the status of the electoral reform process and progress on the implementation of the recommendations. This helped boost transparency and carry momentum forward on electoral reform.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The 2015 elections in Guatemala were marred by a range of issues including campaign finance violations, electoral violence and barriers to participation for women and minorities. The &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.facebook.com/Mirador-Electoral-1436014673391313/&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Mirador Electoral&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; coalition, which includes GNDEM member &lt;a href=&quot;http://accionciudadana.org.gt/&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Acción Ciudadana&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, monitored these issues and others during the pre-election period and on election day. In the months following the elections, they helped advocate for their electoral recommendations to be included in the landmark Law on Elections and Political Parties (LEPP). The final LEPP reform package included about two-thirds of Mirador Electoral’s recommendations. Acción Ciudadana used its campaign finance monitoring effort to show that parties’ expenditures were greatly exceeding campaign income limits. This was vital because it indicated that parties weren’t actually disclosing all of their income, which helped strengthen demand for greater disclosure requirements on both income and expenditure; these were then included in the LEPP. AC’s and Mirador Electoral’s successes in electoral reform were particularly important as citizens and CSOs saw that their involvement and advocacy made a difference, opening opportunities for continued advocacy for additional reforms in the future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The importance of citizen election observers cannot be overstated, especially in utilizing election data collected during observation of electoral processes, developing concrete recommendations for electoral stakeholders, and working to raise awareness and advocate for electoral reforms. This &lt;a href=&quot;http://media4democracy.eu/wp-content/uploads/2018/03/Guide-for-Citizen-Observers-on-Electoral-reform.pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;guide&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, is a step forward in consolidating best practices from citizen observer groups around the world, including many GNDEM members, and is a powerful tool to provide guidance to groups in advocating for and tracking electoral reforms.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Citizen election observation has grown over the past 30 years into a well-established, global movement for enhancing the integrity of elections. Citizen observer groups not only monitor election day processes, but are also involved in pre- and post-election processes and between elections. Groups’ assessments of electoral processes typically include reports at various stages of the election cycle, as well as recommendations on how to best address issues to bring the elections in line with regional and international standards and to improve future electoral processes.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Citizen Observers Discuss Importance Of Monitoring Disinformation In Elections</title><link href="/gndem.org/fr/2018/07/21/citizen-observers-discuss-importance-of-monitoring-disinformation-in-elections.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Citizen Observers Discuss Importance Of Monitoring Disinformation In Elections" /><published>2018-07-21T17:54:03-04:00</published><updated>2018-07-21T17:54:03-04:00</updated><id>/gndem.org/2018/07/21/citizen-observers-discuss-importance-of-monitoring-disinformation-in-elections</id><content type="html" xml:base="/gndem.org/2018/07/21/citizen-observers-discuss-importance-of-monitoring-disinformation-in-elections.html">&lt;p&gt;On March 23, 2018, Mexican citizen observer groups joined together with civic technology groups in Mexico City for a workshop aimed at discussing specific ways the two communities could collaborate to address disinformation ahead of and around Mexico’s 2018 elections.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Disinformation, or the deliberate dissemination or generation of false information intended to manipulate public opinion and discourse, is a growing threat to democracies around the world. It’s a particularly serious problem during electoral processes, as it can stifle citizen participation, amplify false narratives, subvert the will of voters and undermine citizens’ confidence in democratic systems and institutions. In certain cases, it could also increase the potential for electoral violence. Citizen observer groups around the world are confronting the impact of disinformation on electoral integrity in their countries, and are exploring methodologies and tools to incorporate disinformation monitoring in their observation efforts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mexico is scheduled to hold general elections on July 1, 2018, which are being called “the biggest elections in Mexican history” by the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ine.mx/&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;National Electoral Institute&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; (Instituto Nacional Electoral, INE). Mexico has already seen a series of &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.wired.com/2015/08/pro-government-twitter-bots-try-hush-mexican-activists/&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;well-documented&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://elpais.com/internacional/2018/03/21/actualidad/1521628738_165398.html&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;attempts&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; to manipulate the online media environment for political advantage in the past, and given the high-stakes of the upcoming elections, as well as the widespread use of online platforms, the potential for disinformation to impact the electoral and information environment are high. In order to address these issues, the National Democratic Institute (NDI) convened Mexican civic tech groups and citizen election observer groups to discuss ways in which the two communities could share information, tools and resources during the electoral period.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Through a facilitated discussion, both sets of groups aimed to identify and agree upon ways to collaborate more effectively during the 2018 elections, particularly in regard to how disinformation impacts the integrity of elections. Citizen observer groups, who historically have experience monitoring traditional pre-election and election day processes, met with civic tech groups, who are currently observing the media environment, including social media platforms, and providing fact-checking services to counter false narratives. The workshop enabled the two communities to discuss what pieces of information or data they could both provide to the other community, as well as what information would be most useful to receive from the other. They also discussed how others’ data could help to inform their analysis and assessment on the integrity of the elections.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During the discussions, international experts facilitated and contributed to the roundtable, including Serbian citizen election observer group and GNDEM member the &lt;a href=&quot;http://crta.rs/&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Center for Research Transparency and Accountability&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; (CRTA). CRTA, who has monitored several recent elections in Serbia, has also incorporated media monitoring and fact-checking efforts into election observation, helping to monitor and combat the spread of false news. CRTA’s experience helped to provide an important perspective for the citizen observer and civic tech groups.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The roundtable on March 23 built off of a March 21 and 22 conference co-hosted by the INE and NDI on “Disinformation and Elections,” which brought together a broad set of electoral stakeholders, including election officials, civil society, international experts, civic-tech groups, academics, and political parties to discuss the threat to electoral integrity posed by the use of disinformation in Mexico’s 2018 elections. Recordings from the event’s livestream can be found in Spanish (&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=RPR-k9_Jmgw&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Day 1&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=29Gifiz4SXo&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Day 2&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;) and English (&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=2AylF7qGvhw&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Day 1&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=j8aS4mSRtLE&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Day 2&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">On March 23, 2018, Mexican citizen observer groups joined together with civic technology groups in Mexico City for a workshop aimed at discussing specific ways the two communities could collaborate to address disinformation ahead of and around Mexico’s 2018 elections.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">GNDEM Members Convene for Academy on Open Data Analysis and Disinformation Monitoring</title><link href="/gndem.org/fr/2018/07/21/gndem-members-convene-for-academy-on-open-data-analysis-and-disinformation-monitoring.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="GNDEM Members Convene for Academy on Open Data Analysis and Disinformation Monitoring" /><published>2018-07-21T17:45:46-04:00</published><updated>2018-07-21T17:45:46-04:00</updated><id>/gndem.org/2018/07/21/gndem-members-convene-for-academy-on-open-data-analysis-and-disinformation-monitoring</id><content type="html" xml:base="/gndem.org/2018/07/21/gndem-members-convene-for-academy-on-open-data-analysis-and-disinformation-monitoring.html">&lt;p&gt;From April 24-27, 2018, 15 citizen election observer groups from 11 countries, including 10 GNDEM members, convened in Belgrade, Serbia for an academy on information and electoral integrity through open election data analysis and monitoring the spread, prevalence and scope of disinformation during elections. The four-day academy included discussions on methodologies for monitoring disinformation in traditional and social media, methods for using open election data as part of election observation efforts, and various tools and skills for opening and analyzing election data to enhance fact-based findings. GNDEM members identified these issues as highly important to electoral integrity following a similar academy in 2017, and the peer-to-peer learning opportunity allowed members to share recent innovative approaches and learn from one another.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;GNDEM members who participated in the academy are: &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.zgjedhje.al/faqe.php?id=1&amp;amp;l2=115&amp;amp;l3=46&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Society for Democratic Culture&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;(Albania), &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.facebook.com/kriik.al/&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;KRIIK Albania Association&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.kzln.org.al/&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Coalition for Free and Fair Elections&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; (Albania), &lt;a href=&quot;http://most.org.mk/&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Citizens Association MOST&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; (Macedonia), the &lt;a href=&quot;http://cemi.org.me/en/&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Monitoring Center CEMI&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; (Montenegro), &lt;a href=&quot;http://podlupom.org/v2/en&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Pod Lupom&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;(Bosnia and Herzegovina), the &lt;a href=&quot;http://crta.rs/&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Center for Research, Transparency and Accountability&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;(Serbia), &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.cesid.rs/&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Center for Free Elections and Democracy&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; (Serbia), the &lt;a href=&quot;http://isfed.ge/&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;International Society For Fair Elections and Democracy&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; (Georgia), &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.oporaua.org/en&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Civil Network OPORA&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; (Ukraine), &lt;a href=&quot;https://promolex.md/?lang=ro&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Promo-LEX Association&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; (Moldova), and &lt;a href=&quot;http://coalition.kg/en/&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Coalition for Democracy and Civil Society&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; (Kyrgyzstan).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The academy began by taking stock of disinformation in elections, including what tactics are being used, how it manifests in traditional and online media, and how it impacts the integrity of electoral processes. Participants highlighted challenges they have encountered in monitoring, mitigating or combatting disinformation. The Center for Research, Transparency and Accountability (CRTA) in Serbia highlighted their efforts at media monitoring and fact-checking around the country’s most recent elections, and how they formulated messages aimed at countering false or misleading information. The International Society For Fair Elections and Democracy (ISFED) in Georgia discussed how they were structuring and designing their methodology to monitor social media ahead of the presidential election this October, using new tools developed to monitor and analyze the large amount of data associated with social media postings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The academy also focused on the use of open election data, and how advocating for and using official data can be a powerful tool to counter disinformation and misleading content. Transparent and accessible data can help election management bodies combat rumors while increasing citizen observers’ ability to fact-check information. Participants learned about tools that can be used to convert data from into open formats or that can be used to extract large data sets, and were able to practice using such tools to analyze real examples of datasets that would benefit and enhance their observation efforts. Drawing on the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.openelectiondata.net/en/&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Open Election Data Initiative&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;’s Election Data Academy, participating citizen observers learned new techniques and tools for analyzing common election data, such as polling station lists (you can test you knowledge of data analysis by going through the modules &lt;a href=&quot;https://openelectiondata.net/en/academy/&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;here&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;; also available in &lt;a href=&quot;https://openelectiondata.net/es/academy/&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Spanish&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://openelectiondata.net/fr/academy/&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;French&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://openelectiondata.net/my/academy/&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Burmese&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://openelectiondata.net/ar/academy/&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Arabic&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the conclusion of the academy, each participant identified specific points of action that they will take back to their observer groups to enhance their respective election monitoring efforts. As new challenges and tactics are used by those seeking to undermine the credibility of electoral processes, GNDEM members must work to adapt new methodologies and incorporate new tools into their monitoring efforts.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="Central &amp; Eastern Europe" /><category term="Eurasia" /><summary type="html">From April 24-27, 2018, 15 citizen election observer groups from 11 countries, including 10 GNDEM members, convened in Belgrade, Serbia for an academy on information and electoral integrity through open election data analysis and monitoring the spread, prevalence and scope of disinformation during elections. The four-day academy included discussions on methodologies for monitoring disinformation in traditional and social media, methods for using open election data as part of election observation efforts, and various tools and skills for opening and analyzing election data to enhance fact-based findings. GNDEM members identified these issues as highly important to electoral integrity following a similar academy in 2017, and the peer-to-peer learning opportunity allowed members to share recent innovative approaches and learn from one another.</summary></entry></feed>